Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף daf is
well
today's דף daf officially is ל"ד Lamed Daled but we are still
behind.
We pick up on the bottom of ל"א עמוד ב' Lamed Aleph
Amud Bet and what we are dealing with is the fact that
the משנה mishna deals with a case of ספק קידושין ספק גירושין
safek kiddushin safek gerushin and speaks about how in that case where
there's a question if the ערווה ervah is in the picture, what
you do with the צרת ערווה tzaras ervah is חליצה chalitza or
יבום. yibum. But the גמרא gemara distinctly points out that the case
of ספק גירושין safek gerushin isn't really a ספק גירושין, safek gerushin,
it's really a case about a גירושין gerushin that's פסול דרבנן pasul
derabanan
and therefore it's working with the assumption that a classic ספק גירושין
safek gerushin would actually not be meaningful because the woman would retain
her חזקה hazaka and her status as an אשת איש eshes ish
and the co-wife the צרת ערווה tzaras ervah would retain her status
as exempt from יבום. yibum. And that's what the גמרא gemara is
working through and the consequences of the מחמיר mechamir demand חליצה. chalitza.
We could be מחמיר mechamir in some cases without a cost, but
in this case if we were מחמיר mechamir it would come with
a serious cost and therefore we leave it on the דאורייתא d'oraisa
and we say that such a woman is considered still an אשת
איש eshes ish and her co-wife is considered a צרת ערווה tzaras
ervah and she walks away without חליצה. chalitza. So now the גמרא
gemara picks up like this.
I am going to tell you we are in the middle of
ל"א עמוד א' Lamed Aleph Amud Aleph and it says it's the
line that you see the line with the asterisk about exactly in
the middle it starts with the asterisk it says העומדת ha-omedes and
we'll begin one line above that. וגבי גירושין vegabei gerushin says the
גמרא gemara when it comes to גט get מי לא תנן mi
lo tnan did we not have a case of a real ספק
גירושין safek gerushin that would have the same consequences that the co-wife
would get חליצה chalitza you're saying the co-wife just walks away? ותנן
v'tnan we taught in the משנה mishna in גיטין Gittin העומדת ברשות
הרבים ha-omedes bereshus harabim this is a classic case of a ספק
safek a woman was standing in the public domain וזרקו לקרוב לה
מגורשת קרוב לו אינה מגורשת vezarko l'karov lah megureshes karav lo eino
megureshes he threw a גט get he threw a גט get to
his wife it was closer to her she's divorced closer to him
she's not divorced we're not going to worry about the exact type
of קניין kinyan that is being referred to here מחצה על מחצה
mechtza al mechtza it's exactly midpoint so
מחצה על מחצה mechtza al mechtza מגורשת ואינה מגורשת megureshes ve-eino megureshes
she's divorced and not divorced doubtful. ואמרינן ve-amrinan so that's what the
משנה mishna says and then we the גמרא gemara says what do
we say למאי הלכתא lemai hilchasa what's the relevance of her being
doubtfully divorced? דכהן הוא אסורה ליה de-kohen hu asura lei oh my
god excuse me I don't know what this is okay my phone
reacts on me דכהן הוא de-kohen hu so then I'll put it
there I forgot it last time דכהן הוא de-kohen hu that if
he's a כהן kohen she is if his wife is a כהן
kohen he cannot now decide well maybe it wasn't a divorce if
he was a כהן kohen he cannot now decide well maybe it
wasn't a divorce let's stay married no she might be divorced and
now he can't stay married because then it's a problem of a
גרושה grusha he can't remarry her. So that's one נפקא מינה. nafka
mina. ואי ערווה היא ve-i ervah hi and the other נפקא מינה
nafka mina the גמרא gemara gives, now it should be noted this
is not the משנה, mishna, this is what the גמרא gemara in
גיטין Gittin says is the implications of a ספק גירושין. safek gerushin.
ואי ערווה היא צרתה בעיא חליצה ve-i ervah hi tzarasa ba'ei chalitza
if she's an ערווה ervah then her co-wife is a questionable צרת
ערווה tzaras ervah and therefore would not be able to walk off
because the woman might be מגורשת megureshes and therefore the co-wife is
obligated in יבום yibum you can't do יבום yibum because she might
be אינה מגורשת eina megureshes and a צרת ערווה tzaras ervah so
what do you do so בעיא חליצה ba'ei chalitza you need חליצה.
chalitza. So גמרא gemara says look in another גמרא gemara it's interesting
you know sort of self-referential because it's not really a question from
a Tannaitic source but in another גמרא gemara we say that a
genuine ספק גירושין safek gerushin the הלכה halacha is חליצה chalitza no
יבום yibum not that סתם stam she keeps her חזקה hazaka and
she just walks off. ולא אמרינן velo amrinan and we don't say
שאם אתה אומר חולצת מתייבמת she-im ata omer choletzes misyabemes that we're
afraid of being מחמיר mechamir and demanding חליצה chalitza because that would
lead to יבום. yibum. No we don't say that we say let's
demand חליצה chalitza in that case. Okay so so the גמרא gemara
says so you see that in a real ספק גירושין safek gerushin
we are okay with demanding חליצה. chalitza. So the גמרא gemara says
הא איתמרה עלה hayitmara alah no it was said about that רבה
ורב יוסף Rabba ve-Rav Yosef דמי דבייהו d'rami davaihu רבה Rabba and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef both say הכא בשתי כיתי עדים עסקינן hacha
bishtei kiti edim askinan we're actually talking about two pairs of witnesses.
אחת אומרת קרוב לה ואחת אומרת קרוב לו. achas omeres karav lah
ve-achas omeres karav lo. The reason there that she does not retain
her חזקה hazaka the woman who received the גט get and her
חזקה hazaka of being married and the co-wife her חזקה hazaka of
being a צרת ערווה, tzaras ervah, the reason it's not doesn't retain
her חזקה hazaka and then just walk off without anything is because
there is something that opposes the חזקה. hazaka. It's not just a
doubt. If there's just an abstract doubt oh we don't know where
the גט get fell then the הלכה halacha is you retain your
חזקה hazaka and we assume that he remains married but here there
is direct testimony against the חזקה. hazaka. The only thing is it's
contradicted testimony. הכא בשתי כיתי עדים עסקינן hacha bishtei kiti edim askinan
we're talking about two pairs of witnesses. two pairs of witnesses. אחת
אומרת קרוב לו Akhas omeres karov lo ואחת אומרת קרוב לו. v'akhas
omeres karov lo. One pair of witnesses says we definitely saw it
and it was closer to her, and the other one says we
definitely saw it and it was closer to him. So the rabbi
says let's go to the instant replay tape. So, no, that was
the only problem. Okay. דהוי ליה ספיקא דאורייתא. D'havei lei sefika d'oraisa.
So that's a biblical ספק. safek. Now what that means is is
that it creates a ספק safek situation even in the face of
a חזקה. chazakah. חזקה chazakah means status quo. So if you have
an abstract doubt, oh we don't know what happened, okay, keep things
the status quo. But if you have concrete testimony even though it's
contradictory testimony, which is interesting, that pushes the חזקה chazakah aside and
now you're really in the world of doubt. So in that type
of a case it's a real דאורייתא d'oraisa doubt. It's not a
דרבנן d'rabbanan חומרא. chumra. It's a real דאורייתא ספק d'oraisa safek and
therefore no more חזקה chazakah and therefore all we can say is
חליצה נבעי בה. chalitza niv'ei bah.
So therefore that's the case that...
okay.
הוי ספיקא דאורייתא. Havei sefika d'oraisa. ומתניתין דהכא U'masnisin d'haka but here
we're not talking about witnesses. ומתניתין דהכא בכת אחת U'masnisin d'haka b'kas
akhas that says it was one pair of witnesses that were split.
One guy said close to him, one guy said close to her,
meaning here we the case we're talking when we're talking about ספקות
sfekos here it's not about two contradictory pairs of witnesses. דהוי ליה
ספיקא דרבנן D'havei lei sefika d'rabbanan so at most it would be
a rabbinic ספק safek meaning דאורייתא d'oraisa you would go by the
status quo. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. Why did our
משנה Mishnah not talk about ספק? safek? Because here we're talking about
cases where it's ספק, safek, who knows what happened? So the real
דאורייתא d'oraisa הלכה halakhah is you rely on the status quo and
in that case you wouldn't even demand a חליצה. chalitza. How about
the fact that we say in the משנה Mishnah over in גיטין
Gittin that even though there's a status quo you demand חליצה? chalitza?
That's because there's testimony against the status quo. Even though it's contradictory
testimony, that's enough to create a real ספק. safek. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. וממאי דמתניתין דהכא בכת אחת, U'mimai
d'masnisin d'haka b'kas akhas, what makes you say that our משנה Mishnah
should be limited to talking when for example it talks about קידושין
Kiddushin and it says there's a ספק קידושין. safek Kiddushin. What makes
you say that we're limited to talking about like a split testimony?
One witness says one, the other, meaning what I'll call an abstract
doubt, and not direct testimony against it. How do you know? Maybe
our משנה Mishnah is talking about even cases of direct testimony.
So, וממאי דמתניתין בכת אחת u'mimai d'masnisin b'kas akhas דומיא דקידושין. dumya
d'Kiddushin. No, because the case of קידושין Kiddushin is not direct testimony,
two witnesses against two witnesses.
מה קידושין בכת אחת אף גירושין בכת אחת. Ma Kiddushin b'kas akhas
af geirushin b'kas akhas. The same way the case of קידושין Kiddushin
it's like one pair of two witnesses split, one says one, one
says the other, so it's not two witnesses
saying directly testifying against the status quo, the same is true by
גירושין. geirushin. Of course that just begs the question. וקידושין גופייהו V'Kiddushin
gufeihu and how do you know in the case of קידושין Kiddushin
where the משנה Mishnah speaks about like you don't know whether the
ring was thrown closer to her or closer to
him, ממאי דבכת אחת? mimai d'b'kas akhas? How do you know it's
like one split pair? Meaning how do you know it's like just
a question of duh we don't know what happened? דילמא בבתי כיתי
עדים? Dilma b'vei kitoi edim? Maybe the cases that we're talking about
even in the קידושין Kiddushin are contradictory witnesses and therefore applied to
the גירושין geirushin
would undermine the חזקה. chazakah. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אי
בבתי כיתי עדים Ei b'vei kitoi edim if it was about two
pairs of
witnesses תשתרי בלא כלום? tishari b'lo klum? How could you have suggested
earlier, now this is a little bit of problem Rashi and Tosafot
discuss it because it's like self-referential,
okay, it doesn't really prove it based on the משנה, Mishnah, it
really proves based on the presumption that we had before, but I'm
not going to try to solve that problem, I'll just read the
גמרא Gemara the simple way. If it was talking about two contradictory
pairs of witnesses, how could you say before when we said do
a חליצה chalitza in the case of ספק קידושין safek Kiddushin that
we wouldn't care if that חליצה chalitza led to a יבום? yibbum?
Okay, how could you have said that?
תשתרי בלא כלום? Tishari b'lo klum? תמני עדים וקאמרי קרוב לה Tamnei
edim v'ka-amri karov lah there're witnesses that say that the קידושין, Kiddushin,
that the money was really close to her and therefore she really
is married and really the co-wife is a צרת ערווה tzaras ervah
and you're going to say we'not going to be afraid that he
might come to do a יבום? yibbum? ואת אמרת תשתרי בלא כלום?
V'at amret tishari b'lo klum? So how could you have said that?
Of course again the problem is that it's self-referential.
Before we thought you went by the חזקה. chazakah. If you went
by the חזקה chazakah then the woman would be presumed to be
not married in the case of ספק קידושין, safek Kiddushin, the co-wife
would be presumed to be eligible for יבום yibbum and we could
say we're not afraid that it'll lead to יבום yibbum because we
go by חזקה. chazakah. Now we're saying how do you know that
the case isn't when there're contradictory witnesses and you throw out the
חזקה, chazakah, and then we couldn't have said that we weren't afraid
that you would do יבום. yibbum. But okay but that's exactly the
point, maybe you were wrong before. All right, so Rashi and Tosafot
try to figure that out. Anyway we're not going to worry about
that. Okay. ותו V'su says the גמרא. Gemara. So anyway we have
a possibility which is a reasonable argument in the משנה Mishnah that
when you have two contradictory pairs of witnesses it undermines the חזקה
chazakah and then it really would have allowed for a genuine case
of a ספק. safek. We know by גיטין Gittin that we say
that in מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin. So why did our משנה Mishnah
not have that possibility by the גט get in our משנה Mishnah
of two contradictory pairs of witnesses? So one argument is somehow we
know that's not what the משנה Mishnah is talking about. Let's see
now what the גמרא Gemara says. ותו V'su and the גמרא Gemara
says anyway moreover beyond all of this,
I just lost my place. And two, בשני כיתי
עדים נמי ספיקא דרבנן, beshnay kitei edim nami sefeika d'rabbanan, you're wrong.
In two cases of contradictory witnesses because they contradict one another, we
don't say oh there's witnesses against the חזקה, chazaka, throw out the
חזקה. chazaka. We say there's contradictory testimony, throw out all the testimony
and you're back to the חזקה. chazaka. So here's a great question.
What is the הלכה? halacha? If you have a חזקה chazaka and
a ספק, safek, you go by the חזקה. chazaka. Okay? You don't
know what to do, you go by the status quo. If there's
a חזקה chazaka against witnesses, you go by the witnesses. If there's
חזקה chazaka against witnesses but there's contradictory witnesses, so do you say
well once there's direct testimony even if it winds up being contradicted
that's enough to undermine the חזקה chazaka and then you're left with
a blank slate and a ספק? safek? Or do you say throw
out both pairs of witnesses, they contradict one another and you're back
to the חזקה? chazaka? So that's what I think we all would
say. Well that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say now. Before
the גמרא Gemara said the חזקה chazaka becomes neutralized, now the גמרא's
Gemara going to say that's not true. You actually do go back
to the חזקה. chazaka. So let's take a look. Okay, דהא אמרינן
אוקי תרי בהדי תרי, de-ha amrinan okei terei bahadei terei, put two
against two, ואשה אוקמה אחזקה, ve-isha okma achazakah, and have the woman
retain her חזקה. chazaka. Now how do you know you should say
that at a דאורייתא d'Oraisa level?
מידי דהוה אנכסי דבר שטיא, midi de-hava anichsei de-Bar Shatya, like the
story about the property of this person called בר שטיא. Bar Shatya.
Now בר שטיא Bar Shatya seems to might be a name but
also as we're going to see he was somebody that was no
he was somebody that might not always be sane, a
שוטה. shoteh. Yes, a שוטה. shoteh. So the question was, so he
was somebody you know maybe had episodes, psychotic breaks and the question
was when he engaged in certain business transactions was he of the
right mind or not of right mind? So what was the story?
דבר שטיא זבין נכסי. de-Bar Shatya zavin nichsei. He sold some property.
אתו בי תרי, atu bei terei, two witnesses came, ואמרי כשהוא חלים
זבין, ve-amri keshu chalim zavin, he sold it when he was of
right mind. ואתו בי תרי, ve-atu bei terei, and another two witnesses
came and said no, ואמרי כשהוא שוטה זבין, ve-amri keshu shoteh zavin,
he sold it when he was not of right mind. So what
do you do? ואמר רב אשי, ve-amar Rav Ashi, אוקי תרי לבהדי
תרי, okei terei lahadei terei, put two against two, throw them all
out, okay, because they contradict so you wipe the slate so you
basically just reject all of that, וארעא אוקמה בחזקת בר שטיא, ve-ara
okma be-chezkas Bar Shatya, and have the property be assumed still under
the control of בר שטיא. Bar Shatya. That was its default position.
Now there's a what to be talked about about the difference between
a חזקה chazaka when it means ownership of property as opposed to
you know like who was the previous owner who was the owner
until this point as opposed to like a חזקה chazaka about a
status quo of a person. But we're not going to worry about
that right now.
But here at least what you say is if it were a
real ספק safek why don't we say something else I don't know
split it. You know if there's a real ספק safek who owns
property. That's like the first משנה Mishnah in בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia.
Okay but no we say we don't know we throw out all
the witnesses and we go back to the status quo. So you
see that's the real הלכה. halacha. So therefore we're back to the
point. How do we say in a case of גט get we
know that there's a משנה Mishnah in גיטין Gittin that we say
basically is that when there's a ספק גט safek get you do
חליצה. chalitzah. And now we're saying you can't distinguish. Any case whether
it's contradictory witnesses whether it's an abstract doubt, דאורייתא d'Oraisa should be
status quo and not need חליצה. chalitzah. So if you still need
חליצה chalitzah it means we're going to be מחמיר machmir in that
type of a case of ספק גט safek get even though in
principle you could go by חזקה. chazaka. Now if that's true why
did our משנה Mishnah not give a classic ספק גט safek get
if the הלכה halacha is that yes in principle go by חזקה
chazaka but nevertheless play it safe and demand חליצה. chalitzah. If that's
really the הלכה halacha like we say over there in the משנה
Mishnah in גיטין, Gittin, why did we not have that scenario here?
So let's take a look. And now the גמרא Gemara switches gears.
אלא אמר אביי, ella amar Abaye, so therefore אביי Abaye says יגיד
עליו רעו, yagid alav re'o, quoting a פסוק pasuk in איוב, Iyov,
let his friend his friend will tell on him will sort of
will reveal about him. So let's figure it out by the context
and the juxtaposition of the משנה. Mishnah. תנא בקידושין והוא הדין לגירושין.
tana be-Kiddushin ve-hu hadin le-Geirushin. So you know what? As opposed to
emphasizing the fact that the משנה Mishnah gave a different scenario by
גט get to say that the case by קידושין Kiddushin isn't relevant,
no we're saying actually you learn one out from the other. By
קידושין Kiddushin it gives a classic case of a ספק safek that
you threw it and you didn't know who was it closer to
and that has a הלכה halacha of חליצה chalitzah not ייבום. yibum.
So by גט get also the same would be true. If it
was a classic case of a ספק, safek, same הלכה. halacha. Why
did it give a different case by גט? get? To give you
an additional scenario not it's an only not to exclude the example
by קידושין Kiddushin to give you another example by גט. get. Okay,
תנא בקידושין, tana be-Kiddushin, the question of a real ספק, safek, והוא
הדין לגירושין, ve-hu hadin le-Geirushin, the same is true by גט get
if there's a real ספק safek whether the גט get got to
her or not, חליצה chalitzah not ייבום, yibum, forget the חזקה chazaka
that might be true דאורייתא d'Oraisa but rabbinically we're going to say
חליצה. chalitzah. So תנא בגירושין tana be-Geirushin and then it gave an
example by גט get which wasn't a real ספק, safek, was a
גט פסול, get pasul, והוא הדין לקידושין, ve-hu hadin le-Kiddushin, and the
same would be true if you had a קידושין Kiddushin that were
rabbinically פסול. pasul. So the point is do not read these scenarios
in the משנה Mishnah as mutually exclusive. Actually by קידושין Kiddushin he
gave one. of examples, by גירושין geirushin it gave another set of
examples, but they're both true by the other cases as well. Okay,
and now we have come to the conclusion, רבא Rava will nuance
that a little bit, but basically the גמרא Gemara in terms of
the earlier discussion has come to the conclusion that even though in
principle you're right, that when even when there's an abstract ספק safek
and even when there's contradictory witnesses, the principle דאורייתא d'Oraisa is you
go to the חזקה, chazakah, and therefore in the case of ספק
גט, safek get, the ערוה ervah should be בחזקת אשת איש, b'chezkat
eshes ish, the צרה tzarah should be צרת ערוה tzaras ervah שתצא
she'titzai without anything, still at a rabbinic level we're going to be
מחמיר machmir and demand a חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, even though there's costs
to that חומרא chumra like we heard about yesterday and potential downside
we're going to be מחמיר. machmir. And yes, you're right, the same
would be true by גט, get, the משנה Mishnah didn't say it
but it's also true by גט. get. Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
that's what אביי Abaye says. אמר ליה רבא, Amar leh Rava, רבא
Rava says back to him, יגיד עליו רעו, Yagid alav rei'o, if
you can learn out one case from the other, מאי זהו דקתני?
mai zehu d'katani? Why does it say this is the case of
ספק קידושין? safek kiddushin? This is the case of ספק גירושין? safek
geirushin? That sounds like we're being very precise, we're not just giving
here's one or two examples here and one or two examples here.
It says like this is the case, like it doesn't apply in
the other direction. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so here's what
רבא Rava says. כל שיש בקידושין יש בגירושין. Kol she'yesh b'kiddushin yesh
b'geirushin. You're right, one of them is לאו דווקא. lav davka. The
cases by קידושין, kiddushin, a classic ספק, safek, you don't know if
it got close to him or close to her or whatever, that
would be true to a גט get too. Any classic ספק safek
would be true in both scenarios, okay, but the case by גט
get wouldn't be true by the case by קידושין. kiddushin. But ויש
בגירושין, v'yesh b'geirushin, there are cases in this משנה Mishnah that apply
to גט get like all the פסולים psulim of the גט, get,
you didn't have the זמן, zman, you didn't have שני עדים, shnei
eidim, מה שאין בקידושין, mah she'ein b'kiddushin, that don't apply in the
קידושין kiddushin scenario. וזהו דגירושין לאו דווקא, V'zehu d'geirushin lav davka, when
it says this is
the case of ספק גירושין, safek geirushin, wait,
זהו
ספק גירושין. zehu safek geirushin. Oh, when it says this is the
case of גירושין, geirushin, it doesn't mean this to exclude others. Other
things also are to גירושין, geirushin, not just the פסול גט passul
get but a real ספק. safek. So that was לאו דווקא. lav
davka. Okay, however, זהו דקידושין, zehu d'kiddushin, but when it says these
are the cases of פסול קידושין, passul kiddushin, that, למעוטי למטמי? l'mautei
l'tamei?
Oh, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. Thank you. זהו דקידושין לאו
דווקא, Zehu d'kiddushin lav davka, no wait, זהו דגירושין לאו דווקא. zehu
d'geirushin lav davka. אלא משום דתנא זהו בקידושין. Ella mishum d'taneh zehu
b'kiddushin. The only reason it said these are the cases of גירושין
geirushin is not, it doesn't mean to exclude the classic... it doesn't
mean to exclude. It would, גירושין geirushin is not limited. The case
of גירושין geirushin also includes classic ספק. safek. It only said that
because it's saying the word זהו zehu by קידושין. kiddushin. תנא נמי
זהו בגירושין. Tana nami zehu b'geirushin. So that's why it said if
by גירושין geirushin these are the cases of ספק גט, safek get,
but it's really a bigger category, it really includes a classic ספק.
safek. וזהו דקידושין, V'zehu d'kiddushin, but when it says these are the
cases of ספק קידושין, safek kiddushin, למעוטי מאי? l'mautei mai? What's that
excluding? It's excluding the פסולי גט, psulei get, the פסולי גט psulei
get would not apply to קידושין. kiddushin. למעוטי זמן דליכא בקידושין, L'mautei
zman d'leika b'kiddushin, to include the case of the פסולי גט psulei
get that doesn't have by קידושין. kiddushin. So you remember basically, right,
the משנה, Mishnah, right, the משנה Mishnah says like
by קידושין kiddushin it said basically, ספק קרוב לו קרוב לה, safek
karov lo karov lah, ספק קרוב לו קרוב לה, safek karov lo
karov lah, right, that was the cases of זהו, zehu, you know,
ספק קידושין, safek kiddushin, whatever, okay,
that's what the משנה Mishnah says. By גירושין geirushin it said, right,
you know, כתב בכתב
ידו, kasav b'ksav yado, you know, בכתב ידו ואין עליו עדים, b'ksav
yado v'ein alav eidim,
עדים, eidim, then it had a case of אין בו זמן ein
bo zman and
then it had a case of עד אחד. ed echad. Okay, then
it says זהו ספק גירושין. zehu safek geirushin. Okay, so
the point is what was bothering us is what about the classic
ספק safek by גירושין. geirushin. So we spent yesterday saying oh in
that case the הלכה halakhah would be different because you would go
by the חזקה chazakah and you wouldn't even be מחמיר machmir for
a חליצה. chalitzah. Now we said no, it's not true, it is
true you would go by the חזקה דאורייתא, chazakah d'Oraisa, but it's
also true that forget about the דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, דרבנן d'Rabbanan we're going
to demand a חליצה chalitzah and the same הלכה halakhah would apply.
So if the same הלכה halakhah would apply, what's the זהו zehu
that seems to say only this? So what רבא Rava says is
this זהו zehu is really לאו דווקא. lav davka. This case of
גירושין geirushin is a bigger category, this would also be true here,
you would demand a חליצה. chalitzah. But the זהו zehu here is
דווקא, davka, because the cases of קידושין kiddushin don't include the cases
of גירושין. geirushin. If you had a scenario like this, now by
the way where are you getting a scenario about a written document
by קידושין, kiddushin, because we'd be talking about קידושי שטר, kiddushei shtar,
not about קידושין, kiddushin, we're talking about קידושי שטר kiddushei shtar not
about קידושי כסף. kiddushei kesef. So if you had a קידושי שטר
kiddushei shtar that was written with these problems, it would not be
the same issue by קידושין. kiddushin. קידושין Kiddushin is limited to these
ספיקות, sveikos, these problems which are not really ספיקות, sveikos, which are
פסולי דרבנן, psulei d'Rabbanan, don't apply to
קידושין, kiddushin, okay, סגי במנה ומדי. sagi b'mana u'midei. So ובזהו דקידושין
תנא tana להו *u'be-zehu de-Kiddushin tana le-hu*
no okay ובזהו דקידושין למיעוטי מאי *u'be-zehu de-Kiddushin l'miyutei mai*? Which cases
is it excluding that would not be relevant to קידושין kiddushin, *Kiddushin*?
למיעוטי זמן zman דליכא בקידושין *miyutei zman de-leika be-Kiddushin*, that the lack
of זמן zman. *zman* would not make a פסול posul שטר קידושין
shtar kiddushin *pasul shtar kiddushin*. The lack of two עדים Eidim *edim*
would, even if it was written in his handwriting. עד אחד *ed
echad* would, that would be a פסול pasul, שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin.
*pasul shtar kiddushin* and that would have the same הלכה Halacha. *halacha*,
but one of these, this one is only relevant by גירושין *geirushin*.
The case of not having a date, that פסול pasul *pasul*s a
גט get. *get*, but it would not פסול passul *pasul* a שטר
קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin* and that's why we said זהו *zehu*,
not to exclude this from down here, but to exclude this problem
of lacking a date, that wouldn't be a problem by a שטר
קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar kiddushin*. And now we're just going to focus
on why that's true. Why is the lack of a date in
the document a problem by a גט get *get* and not a
problem by a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin. *shtar kiddushin*? So let's take
a look. ומפני מה לא תיקנו זמן בקידושין *u'mipnei mah lo tiknu
zman be-Kiddushin*? Why did they not demand for a date in a
שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin, *shtar kiddushin*, the Rabbis, and then say that
it would be rabbinically invalid without it? So, הני ניחא למאן דאמר
משום פירי ארוסה לית לה פירי arusa leis la peiri, *hani nicha
le-man d'amar mishum peiri, arusah leisa peiri*. So there's a question, why
did they demand a date in a גט get *get*? Why do
you need a date in a גט get *get*? So what's the
most obvious reason why you need a date in a גט get
*get*?
So you know when she's divorced. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says
well, okay, what do you mean, but if she wants to get
remarried she'll take out her גט get *get*. Who needs a date?
Any time she takes it out. What? If she's pregnant. Exactly, so
you'll know maybe if there was some activity in the past what
exactly the story was. So that's the easiest explanation. The way the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames that is שמא יחפה על בת אחותו *shema
yichapel bas achoso*. Maybe he'll try to protect his niece. Meaning, imagine
that if a man is divorcing his wife he wouldn't really care
about her, unless she was anyway related to him from a different
direction, so maybe he had married his niece. So anyway but the
basic point being maybe he's trying to protect his wife. So even
though he's divorcing her, let's say she committed adultery and he's divorcing
her, but nevertheless he wants to protect her. So what he's going
to do is he's going to predate a גט get. *get*, so
she can basically say that she was divorced
before this act of adultery occurred, at least save her from getting
executed by the court. Okay, so that's one explanation. What?
She's pregnant. Yeah, or say the kid's from being a ממזר *mamzer*.
What? Right, exactly. So the other possibility is much more mundane, which
is that from the moment a woman is divorced
then
the husband is no longer entitled to eat the, it's called usufruct,
to eat the נכסי מלוג *nichsei milug*, to eat the fruit
that grows from the woman's property. Okay,
so then he would have no... so what would be the issue?
If you don't date it then he's more entitled to keep on
taking the fruit. So the concern is the following. Look at רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* explains it, so it says בגיטין בפרק
כל הגט *be-Gittin be-perek kol ha-Get*, מפני מה תיקנו חכמים זמן בגט
משום פירי למידע מאימתאי תבעי מבעלה פירות שאכל מנכסי מלוג שלה *mipnei
mah tiknu chachamim zman be-Get mishum peiri, leida mei-eimasai tiv'ei mi-ba'alah peiros
she-achal mi-nichsei milug she-lah*. So basically when can she collect from her
husband, excuse me, מבעלה פירות שאכל מנכסי מלוג *mi-ba'alah peiros she-achal mi-nichsei
milug*. When can she collect the fruit that he's eating from her
stuff from the moment she's divorced? So we have to have proof
when she's divorced. Now that should be in the husband's self-interest to
write the זמן *zman*. דסבר משום ששעה שנתן עיניו לגרשה שוב אין
לו לבעל פירות *de-svar mishum she-sha'ah she-nasan einav la-gareshah shuv ein lo
le-ba'al peiros*. So the question of course is maybe he signed... he
wrote the date on the גט Get. *get*, maybe he wrote the
date on the גט Get *get* before he actually gave her the
גט Get *get*. It doesn't matter. From the time you're writing the
גט Get *get*, you forfeit the right to the benefit from the
fruit. Okay, so therefore it's in the husband's interest right not to
put the date on the גט Get *get*, right? It's in the
husband's interest not to put the date on the גט Get *get*.
Oh, I'm sorry, so here's the problem. I'm sorry, I misstated before.
Let's go back for a second to the case about trying to
protect his wife from a charge of adultery. So once we demand
the date on a גט Get, *get*, we're not concerned about predating,
because witnesses have to sign it. Okay, so we're not concerned about
actually forging the date. Witnesses won't sign it if it's forged. But
we demand a date because if we didn't demand a date, you'd
give your wife a גט Get *get* without a date and she
would claim that it was from before the act of adultery. Once
we demand a date, we're not afraid of predating. The witnesses will
ensure that won't happen. Similarly here. So that's why we demand a
date. Similarly here, you'll write a גט Get *get* for your wife
and not date it. Why? So that any time she says look
I'm divorced you have to give me the fruit that you took
from my property, he says no I just divorced you yesterday. It
hasn't been five years, it was yesterday. So once we demand that
it be dated, then it'll be the right date and then the
woman will be getting her fruit from the time that she's entitled.
Okay, so those are the two reasons. משום פירי *mishum peiri* and
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* calls משום בת אחותו *mishum bas achoso*.
How do you translate the word מלוג *milug* in that?
I'm not going to talk about... we'll talk about that when we
get to it later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, so ומפני מה לא תיקנו זמן בקידושין? הניחא למאן דאמר
משום פירי, ha-nicha le-man d'amar mishum peiri, if the reason for the
date is to entitle, make sure the woman gets back the fruit
from her property that she's entitled to and the husband doesn't claim
I just divorced you yesterday. So ארוסה לית לה פירי, so there's
no purpose of pointing, putting out the date in the שטר קידושין
shtar kiddushin? because the husband isn't entitled to the fruit from the
time of קידושין, kiddushin. he's only entitled to it from the time
of נשואין. nissu'in. So why do you need the date? Right, no
ownership of property switches at the time of קידושין. kiddushin So if
the focus is so but it doesn't matter, it's not relevant for
the question of ownership of property. So if the reason of the
date is to ensure proper ownership of property, it's not relevant for
שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin? So then we understand why it's not a
problem not to have a date. אלא, ella, says the גמרא, Gemara
that's fine. אלא למאן דאמר משום בת אחותו, ella le-man d'amar mishum
bas achoso,
if the problem, if the need for the date for the date
for the date is to ensure that, you know, somebody doesn't cover
up an act of adultery, you know exactly when she was divorced,
so לתקין זמן, litkin zman, so the same thing should demand that
we have a date in the שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin. so that
you know when she was married and when she wasn't married. So
if there are questions similarly there about adultery or whatever, you know,
what will happen? You give her, I mean, you give her a
שטר קידושין Shtar Kiddushin, without a date, then she commits adultery and
then she claims, no, I just got married, I just got married
yesterday after the act with that other man. Okay, so we should,
if we're concerned about that, we should similarly be concerned that we
have accurate information about that. אלא, ella, so that's the גמרא's Gemara,
question. So the answer is, משום דאיכא דמיקדש בכספא ואיכא דמיקדש בשטרא
לא תיקנו רבנן זמן. mishum de-ika de-mikadesh be-chaspa ve-ika de-mikadesh be-shtara lo
tiknu rabbanan zman. What it says is look, often enough we're not
going to have precise knowledge about when she got married anyway because
people marry with money much more often than with a שטר קידושין.
Shtar Kiddushin. I once had a couple that came and asked me,
they said we want to do קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara. I said,
excuse me. Anyway, so I did some research, it was quite fascinating,
and even though there's like almost no גמרא Gemara on it, like
three lines of גמרא Gemara of discussion on it, there are no
cases in the גמרא Gemara about it. There's all these cases about
קידושי כסף, kiddushei chesef, no cases of קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara. I
contacted
Mordechai Friedman, Friedman, who is
who did all the work with the Cairo Genizah and all of
the כתובות kesubos and all of the stuff about marriages, and he
says in all of that evidence, he says we have not one
instance of קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara. So so I said, I don't
think there's absolutely any מסורה masorah about this, but I'm not doing
any קידושי שטרא kiddushei shtara with you guys. Anyway, so, but the
גמרא, Gemara so it's funny, the גמרא Gemara says some people do
it this way, some people do it that way. The evidence is
everybody does קידושי כסף, kiddushei chesef, nobody does קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara.
Anyway, the point is, often enough, if not the vast majority of
times, there's no concrete evidence of what the date of קידושין kiddushin.
was anyway. And since it's not happening by כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin,
we're not going to go ahead all of a sudden you decide
to do בשטרא, be-shtara, all of a sudden now we're going to
be worried about knowing the date? You're not worried about knowing the
date when it's קידושי כסף, kiddushei chesef, so we're not going to
make a sense to invalidate a שטר shtar and require it all
of a sudden because you're doing it with a שטר. shtar. You
could even when you make a שטר shtar you put in the
date. Okay, but we're not going to פסול it without it. דאיכא
דמיקדש בכספא ודאיכא דמיקדש
בשטרא. d'ika d'mikadesh be-chaspa ve-d'ika d'be-shtara.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי, amar leh Rav Aha breih de-Rav Yosef
le-Rav Ashi, והא עבדים, ve-ha avadim, slaves? דאיכא דקני בכספא ואיכא
בשטרא, d'ika de-kani be-chaspa ve-ika be-shtara, some people buy slaves with money
and some with documents, ותקינו רבנן זמן, ve-tiknu rabbanan zman,
and the Rabbis demanded that there be a date in that document?
Why we don't have to worry about, but the point is even
though you don't always do it with a שטר? shtar? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, התם רובא בשטרא, hasam rova be-shtara, which makes
sense, obviously people want a document to prove ownership of their slaves,
right? It's property and they want it documented. So therefore we're going
to demand זמן and we won't worry about the exceptions when it's
done with כסף. kesef. הכא רובא בכסף, hacha rova be-chesef, and now
the גמרא Gemara. tells us that here the majority, the vast majority
is with כסף. kesef. We're not going to all of a sudden
say when you switch gears and do it, all of a sudden
now we're going to get worried about having it dated. Okay, so
that's one answer. So that's why this case here, these problems are
not all problems by קידושין. Kiddushin, The אין בו זמן ein bo
zman is only a גיטין Gittin problem. איבעית אימא, ibayis eima, yeah?
What about the...
isn't that always given?
No,
כתובה kesubah is given at the נשואין, nissu'in, which often would be
yeah, which often would be a good deal afterwards. איבעית אימא משום
דלא אפשר, ibayis eima mishum d'lo efshar, or here's another reason why
we don't have the date in a שטר shtar. קידושין, kiddushin because
it's not possible. Meaning, it's possible but it wouldn't do any good.
Why wouldn't it do any good? היכי נעביד? heichi ne'avid? What do
you want to do with this שטר Shtar. קידושין? Kiddushin, ננחיה גבי
דידה, nanchayei gabei didah, have her hold onto the שטר Shtar קידושין?
kiddushin מחקה ליה, machka leh, so
so what? The whole reason to have a date is so that
we can prove when she committed adultery. So if she doesn't have
the date, then she can always say that she got married later.
So guess what? She's not the right person to be holding onto
the שטר. Shtar, Okay? Erase it, or whoops, I can't find my
שטר Shtar קידושין. So that's not going to do any good. So
ליהוי גבי דידיה. Lihvei gabei didei. So say, okay, after you give
your wife a שטר Shtar. קידושין, you hold on to the שטר.
Shtar So זימנין דבתר חותנו מחפה לה. Zimnin d'basar chosno mechapei lah.
Same problem. Maybe he'll want to protect her. It's a similar case
of a נס, nes, same way he'll protect her with a גט.
Get Whoops, can't find the שטר Shtar. קידושין. Okay. ליהוי גבי עדים.
Linhvei gabei eidim.
Have the witness have like some third party, the witnesses who witnessed
the שטר Shtar hold on to it. אי דדכירי, Ei d'dachiri, look,
that won't help you. If anyway they remember what they saw, you
know, the date that they saw the קידושין, ליתו וליסהדו, Leisavu v'lisahadu,
they'll come and testify on their own. ואי לא, V'ei lo, and
if they don't remember, זימנין דחזו, Zimnin d'chazu, look at the
שטר, זימנין דחזו מהאי כתבא, Zimnin d'chazu me'hai ksav, and they'll come
and they'll testify based on what they read in the document, not
based on their actual memory. ורחמנא אמר מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם, V'rachmana
amar mipichem v'lo mipi ksavm, and you can only testify based on
what you remember, you can't testify based on something you wrote down.
So therefore it's not going to do any good.
So the גמרא Gemara. says אי הכי בגירושין נמי, Ei hachi b'gerushin
nami, so by a גט Get also won't do any good to
have the זמן. Okay? Because people will just get rid of it
or erase it. Of course there's an obvious answer. By a גט
Get she's assumed to be מקודשת. mekudeshet. She needs to produce the
גט Get to get her off. So there's no way the גט
Get can whoops be lost. Okay. נימא הכי. Neima hachi. No. התם
להצלה דידה קאתי. Hasam l'hatzala didah ka'asi. There you need to produce
the גט Get to protect her. So הכא לחובתא דידה קאתי. Hacha
l'chovsa didah ka'asi. Here the existence of the שטר is a detriment,
so you'll lose the שטר. Okay? What? Same problem? I mean, the
בית דין Beis Din still, the idea is similar to the concern
by the עדים and so on. The בית דין Beis Din can't
testify מתוך הכתב. m'toch haksav. Now I want to say something very
briefly. It's a fascinating issue מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם mipichem v'lo mipi
ksavm given the time we can't really explore it further, but I
just want to say two important points about it. Number one is
תוספות Tosafos says I don't understand. The whole point about signing a
שטר is is that the document testified can be produced as evidence.
So what do you mean the witnesses will read it and testify
and they won't have remembered it? Don't read it. Don't testify. Just
come and deliver the document to the court. And let the signed
document serve. And תוספות Tosafos says you know what? That's right. That
would totally work. But the problem is we're afraid that they won't
do that. They'll read it and say oh yeah, and then they'll
come and they'll say second-hand and they won't produce the document. But
of course if they actually would just produce the document and not
say anything, we would go by the document. That's the whole point
about a signed document. Point number one. Point number two is that
not only that, but actually if you use something to prompt your
memory, forget that it's a signed שטר. You write a little note
in a diary. And you re-read the diary and then you actually
do recall the event. Now of course we know that memory is
completely fallible and influenced by things that we, other types of things,
but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara actually says that you're allowed to remind
your use those things to remind yourself if in the end you're
testifying based on what you remember, not based on because you saw
it written there. You actually don't remember, but I'm saying it happened
because I saw it was written in my diary. That would be
invalid. But if it actually caused you to remember, that would be
valid. So the interesting thing about this scenario is that there's two
cases which would be fine. Just produce the document. Or help it
remind you and then testify based on what you genuinely remember. The
only case that's not good is to testify about the event that
you don't remember and you're not producing the document, but you're testifying
it because you read it in the document. Okay, and that would
be the problematic case.
Great point, what if he just had handwritten notes and that would
serve as a
memory jog, but he might rely more on a written document right
that even though I don't remember I can testify because I saw
it written in the גט. Get Exactly. Okay. So that's exactly it.
Now I'll read you also, see I said I wasn't going to
do it but I can't resist.
So it says, and if you take a look here, right, so
take a look at תוספות Tosafos דחזו d'chazu like three lines before
it gets wide, he says ואומר ר"י דהכא נמי אם היו מעידים
שכך ראו בשטר. v'omer Ri d'hacha nami im hayu me'idim shekach ra'u
bashtar. If they actually didn't just claim they remembered when they didn't,
but they either produced the document or testified what they saw in
the document, שפיר הוו עבדי. shapir havu avdi. That would work. דהרי
הם כאילו מעידים בבואם עדותן שנתקבלה בבית דין. deharei heim k'ilu me'idim
b'vuam eidosan sheniskabla b'beis din. והעדים החתומים על השטר נעשו כמי שנחקרה
עדותן בבית דין. v'ha'eidim hachasumim al hashtar na'asu k'mi shenichkra eidosan b'beis
din. אבל חיישינן שמא לא יעידו שכך ראו בשטר אלא שמא יעידו
על המעשה עצמו כאילו הם זוכרים ואין הם זוכרים אלא על פי
הכתב.
aval chaishinan shema lo ya'idu
shekach ra'u bashtar ela shema ya'idu al hama'aseh atzmo k'ilu heim zochrim
v'ein heim zochrim ela al pi haksav. Okay. And then the גמרא
Gemara says right אלא וכן הא דאמר בפרק ב' דכתובות כותב אדם
עדותו על השטר ומעיד עליה אפילו אחר כמה שנים והוא שזוכרה מעצמו
אבל אין זוכרה מעצמו לא.
ela v'chein ha d'amar b'perek
beis d'kesubos kosev adam eidoso al hashtar u'me'id aleha afilu achar kama
shanim v'hu shezochra me'atzmo aval ein zochra me'atzmo lo. התם נמי לא
איירי בדאמר שכך ראו כתוב אלא בדאמר על המעשה עצמו. hasam nami
lo airy b'de'amar shekach ra'u kasuv ela b'de'amar al hama'aseh atzmo. Okay.
So and ועוד התם לא הוי שטר אלא שכתב לזכרון
דברים
בעלמא.
v'od hasam lo havi shtar ela shekasav
l'zichron devarim b'alma. Okay, etc., etc. So therefore
it says as well there that... now again there's a subject question
of what does it mean זוכרה מעצמו zochra me'atzmo as opposed to
לא זוכרה מעצמו. lo zochra me'atzmo. How much is the שטר serving
as a prompt? and how much do you genuinely really remember it?
But again the primary issue is is that you have to actually
be testifying based on what you remembered. But if you testify it
was written in a signed document, that's okay. The problem is when
you testify that you remembered it and you actually are not remembering
it, but you're just getting that information elsewhere. Okay, and I want
to just add one other line that again I can't resist, because
this is a fascinating point about what's it called, about
a deposition. ואומר ר"י, v'omer Ri, דשמע רבינו תם, d'shama Rabbeinu Tam,
שנוהגים עכשיו, shenohagim achshav, the next line in תוספות, Tosafos, ששולחים העדים
עדותן בכתב ידם לבי"ד, shesholchim ha'edim edusan bichsav yadam l'beis din, that
you can actually write out your testimony and send it. So that's
different. That's not your testifying on something written that you didn't actually
witness or you don't actually remember, but you're communicating your testimony through
writing. לא קרינא ביה מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם, כיון שהם זוכרים עדותן.
lo karina bei mi pihem v'lo mi pi kisavam, keivan she'hem zochrim
edusan. Since there you do remember, the form of communication is through
writing, that's okay. Okay, the problem is when you don't actually remember
and you're testifying as if you remember based on something you saw
written. Alright. Yes? Translator?
That's exactly then what תוספות Tosafos works out. How does that work
with the issue of translator and the whole thing? But that reflects
a reality that they couldn't always have people traveling and showing up
in court. So the rest of the תוספות Tosafos works that through.
Okay, let's now look at the משנה. mishna. ג' אחין נשואין ג'
נכריות, Gimmel achin nesuin gimmel nochriyos, ומת אחד מהן. umes echad mehen.
Okay, three brothers married to three unrelated women and one of them
dies.
ועשה בה השני מאמר, v'asah ba hasheini ma'amar, and the second one
did a מאמר ma'amar with this available woman. ומת, umes, and then
he dies. So here the case
is, ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי. Levi. Okay, ראובן Reuven is
married to I don't know, רחל, Rachel, שמעון Shimon is married to
דבורה, Dvora, לוי Levi is married to חולדה. Chulda. Oh god. What?
So anyway, okay. So one of the brothers died, okay, and now
שמעון, Shimon, we decided what blue was our מאמר ma'amar color, he
did מאמר ma'amar with רחל, Rachel, okay, and then שמעון Shimon died,
okay? Now לוי Levi here doesn't really matter who לוי's Levi married
to. Okay, he has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum to דבורה
Dvora coming from שמעון, Shimon, right? He has a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibbum to רחל Rachel coming from ראובן, Reuven, coming from ראובן,
Reuven, right? He could have done יבום yibbum down here too. But
since שמעון Shimon did מאמר, ma'amar,
שמעון Shimon is now quasi-married to רחל Rachel as well, right? What's
the whole טעם ta'am of מאמר? ma'amar? So he also has a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum to רחל, Rachel, a quasi מצוה mitzvah
from שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so here he actually has a מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibbum to one woman based on two separate brothers. Okay,
so this is the issue the משנה mishna deals with.
So let's take a look.
הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות. harei elu choltzos v'lo misyabmos.
Both women, דבורה Dvora and רחל, Rachel, get חליצה chalitza and not
יבום. yibbum. So why רחל Rachel is problematic we understand. Why דבורה's
Dvora problematic is a lot less clear. Let's see why רחל Rachel
is problematic. שנאמר, shene'emar, so the verse says, ומת אחד מהן, umes
echad mehen, one of the brothers dies, then יבמה יבוא עליה. yevamah
yavo aleha. מי שעליה זיקת יבם אחד, mi she'aleha zikas yavam echad,
only a woman that he's connected to through one of his through
one brother, ולא שעליה זיקת שני יבמין, v'lo she'aleha zikas shenei yevamin,
not a woman that basically is connected through two brother-in-laws, or for
him from his perspective, from two brothers. So this woman רחל Rachel
is basically, if שמעון Shimon had fully married her, ראובן Reuven would
have been out of the picture if he had done יבום. yibbum.
Then both of the women would have come to him through שמעון.
Shimon. But since he didn't do יבום, yibbum, ראובן Reuven is still
in the picture and now he's got her coming to him from
two brothers. That's excluded. Now, most say that if מאמר ma'amar is
דרבנן, derabbanan, this whole דרשה drasha is דרבנן. derabbanan. Okay, but if
מאמר ma'amar has some דאורייתא d'oraysa weight like we've seen by בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, then it's possible that רחל Rachel could really be
in a quasi position and still have two זיקות. zikos. Let's see
the end of the משנה. mishna. ר' שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer,
מיבם לאיזו שירצה וחולץ לשניה. miyabem l'eizo sheyirtzeh v'choleitz lashniya. ר' שמעון
Rebbi Shimon doesn't buy this. He basically says either מאמר ma'amar is...
as opposed to saying מאמר ma'amar is fifty percent, ר' שמעון Rebbi
Shimon says it's either a hundred percent or zero. So if it's
a hundred percent, then רחל Rachel was totally married to שמעון, Shimon,
ראובן's Reuven out of the picture, so he can do יבום yibbum
to רחל Rachel or דבורה. Dvora. If מאמר ma'amar was zero, then
רחל Rachel is not related to שמעון, Shimon, coming from ראובן, Reuven,
and he also could do יבום yibbum with רחל. Rachel. So if
it's fifty percent, you got your problem; he's both ראובן Reuven and
שמעון. Shimon. But it's not, it's a hundred percent or zero. Now,
why can't he do יבום yibbum with both? Well, if מאמר ma'amar
was nothing, he could do יבום yibbum with both. They're coming from
different brothers. But if מאמר ma'amar worked, then they're both coming from
שמעון, Shimon, and you can't do יבום yibbum with two wives from
the same brother, right? You do יבום yibbum with one and then
have or חליצה chalitza and everybody else gets off. So because it
might have worked, he can only do יבום yibbum with one. Because
it might not have worked, then he has to do חליצה chalitza
with the other. another woman. Okay, just doing יבום yibbum with רחל
Rachel won't be enough, 'cause maybe מאמר ma'amar didn't work and she
was up here with ראובן Reuven and דבורה Devora is still waiting
for something to happen. So you can't do יבום yibbum with both,
'cause they could be coming from the same brother. But so you
have to do, and you can't just do יבום, yibbum, 'cause they
could be coming from opposite brothers. So you have to do יבום
yibbum with one, חליצה chalitza with the other. So that's רבי שמעון.
Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's either hundred or zero.
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says she's fifty percent, so therefore יוחל Yochal
has the problem, so you know why you gotta do חליצה chalitza
with רחל. Rachel. What you don't know is why can't you go
ahead and do יבום yibbum with דבורה. Devora. Okay, so we'll take
a look at that in the גמרא. Gemara Yes?
You could also have this discussion for the case of יש זיקה
yesh zika when there's no מאמר. ma'amar.
Right. Moving on. Okay. אי זיקת בית יבמין דאורייתא Ei zikat beit
yavmin de'oraisa says the גמרא. Gemara One minute.
If this is a דאורייתא de'oraisa problem that רחל Rachel has a
quasi status and this is a real פסול, so חליצה נמי לא
תיבעי. chalitza nami lo tibaye. So why do we say that רחל
Rachel needs חליצה? chalitza? If the תורה Torah is excluding a woman
with this double status, so then exclude her. Let her walk off.
אלא מדרבנן. Ela miderabbanan. You're right. This whole idea of a double
status is only a דרבנן derabbanan problem. Probably because מאמר ma'amar is
a whole דרבנן derabbanan issue. Fine. And because the whole thing is
a דרבנן derabbanan problem, we're still, you still got to do something
with רחל, Rachel, so you still need חליצה. chalitza. גזירה שמא יאמרו
שתי יבמות הבאות מבית אחד מתייבמות. Gezeira shema yomru shtei yevamot haba'ot
mibeit echad mityabmot.
Because here's the point. דאורייתא De'oraisa there's no problem with רחל. Rachel.
דאורייתא De'oraisa this is nothing. דאורייתא De'oraisa לוי Levi could do יבום
yibbum with רחל Rachel and יבום yibbum with דבורה. Devora. But we
don't like that. Because the way people look at it, you know,
ראובן Reuven might have died ten years ago. Everybody's forgotten about ראובן.
Reuven. שמעון Shimon has done קידושין with רחל. Rachel. People think רחל
Rachel is שמעון's Shimon wife. And people are going to now see
לוי Levi do יבום yibbum with both. They're going to think that
a brother married to two wives, the surviving brother can do יבום
yibbum with both of the wives. And that's obviously not true. Once
you do יבום yibbum with one, the other wife, you'll do חליצה
chalitza with one, the other wife gets off. So because people think
that רחל Rachel is שמעון's Shimon wife, we don't let him do
יבום yibbum with both.
We know why we're not going to allow יבום yibbum with both.
We know why we're going to demand חליצה. chalitza. And we're going
to situate the problem with רחל. Rachel. So we're not going to
allow יבום yibbum with רחל Rachel 'cause anyway, 'cause she's the one
that sort of is the source of this conflict, of this issue.
So her we're going to demand חליצה. chalitza. This פסול of two
אחים achim we're going to דרבנן derabbanan we're going to demand חליצה.
chalitza. But if as long as you say that דאורייתא de'oraisa this
really is not, you know, there's no relationship, let him do חליצה
chalitza with רחל Rachel and let him do יבום yibbum with דבורה.
Devora. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this. וניבם לחדא ונחלוץ
לחדא. V'neiyabeim l'chada v'neichlotz l'chada.
Do יבום yibbum with one and חליצה chalitza with the other. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. גזירה שמא יאמרו בית אחד מקצתו בנוי
ומקצתו חלוץ. Gezeira shema yomru beit echad miktzato banuy umiktzato chalutz.
Same problem. People will think that both of them are his wives
and they'll think look, he did יבום yibbum with one and חליצה
chalitza with the other, so in general if a brother dies and
has two wives you gotta do יבום yibbum with one and חליצה
chalitza with the other, which you could imagine people thinking, right? There
are multiple wives, so you do יבום yibbum with one and חליצה
chalitza with the other. Okay so we don't want people to think
that. The גמרא Gemara says ויאמרו. v'yomru. Who cares? Let them think
it. So what are you going to do? Big deal. So you
do a few extra חליצות. chalitzas. Who cares? Okay so great, do
יבום yibbum with one and חליצה chalitza with the other even though
you don't need, what's the big deal, what's the cost? Not that
you should do it but who cares if people make that mistake.
גמרא Gemara says no. אי דמיבם והדר חליץ. Ei de'miyabeim vehadar chalitz.
You're right. If normally a guy died, left a few wives, and
the brother does יבום yibbum with the one and then does חליצה
chalitza with the others, הכי נמי, hachi nami, then okay, it was
silly but there was no cost, no loss. He did חליצה chalitza
with women who didn't require it. Of course maybe you'll פסול them
for כהונה. kehunah. Okay. אלא Ela but even so maybe you know,
בית דין Beit Din will then know better, but at least it
won't be cost to the act of חליצה chalitza itself. אלא גזירה
Ela gezeira here's the concern. If people think you do both, דילמא
חליץ ברישא והדר מיבם. dilma chalitz bereisha vehadar miyabeim. First you'll do
חליצה chalitza to the woman he's not interested in, and then you'll
do יבום yibbum with the other one. That is a problem because
once you've done the first act of חליצה chalitza you've excluded all
the other wives from
יבום. yibbum. וקאי עליה באשר לא יבנה, V'ka'ei aleia ba'asher lo yivneh,
that once he's in the category of that he is not building
up the house, then he can't marry the remaining sisters once he's
done חליצה chalitza with, you know, sisters-in-law once he's done חליצה chalitza
with one.
רחמנא אמר כיון שלא בנה שוב לא יבנה. Rachmana amar keivan shelo
bana shuv lo yivneh. Okay now you could say okay, so I
get that this look, רחל Rachel looks like שמעון's Shimon wife and
because looks like שמעון's Shimon wife we're not going to allow him
to do יבום yibbum with both, we're not going to allow him
to do יבום yibbum and חליצה chalitza because that'll lead to another
case of two wives where people will do יבום yibbum and חליצה
chalitza and if they do it in the wrong order you got
a problem. We're going to demand two חליצות. chalitzas. Because that comes
with no cost. Because what will happen? Another brother will die with
five wives, so you do five חליצות. chalitzas. Okay big deal, right?
I mean the cost might be the כהונה kehunah issue but the
act of חליצה chalitza בית דין Beit Din hopefully again will know
better, but the act of חליצה chalitza will come at no cost.
So the גמרא's Gemara explaining why the משנה Mishna frames it as
a type of a דאורייתא De-Oraisa problem with רחל Rachel having a
dual status. A, that would explain why רחל Rachel gets חליצה, Chalitzah,
and B, it wouldn't explain why you can't do יבום Yibum with
דבורה. Devorah. So the גמרא Gemara therefore reframes it as a גזירה
Gezeira that they both look like ראובן's Reuven wife, and the only
way to play it safe in that case and to שמעון's Shimon
wife, and the only way to play it safe is do חליצה
Chalitzah with both. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Why not do יבום Yibum with דבורה Devorah though?
Because then people, that's exactly what it said, then the next time
somebody will do יבום Yibum with one wife and חליצה Chalitzah with
the other, and they'll do it in the wrong order, and whatever.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא נתן גט למאמרו,
Amar Rava nosan get le-maamaro, so now we're going to deal with,
so now we got this problem. Now רבא Rava says let's say
the guy came and gave, after מאמר, Maamar, remember מאמר's Maamar an
act of קידושין, it's really giving כסף Kesef and saying הרי את
מקודשת לי, Harei at mekudeshes li, it's just in the context of
יבום. Yibum. So therefore it's called מאמר Maamar so you don't think
it's at דאורייתא De-Oraisa level. So he gave, he did a מאמר
Maamar with רחל. Rachel. Now before he died,
you know what he did? He decided he's no longer interested in
רחל, Rachel, and he gave her a גט. Get Okay? And then
he died. Is רחל Rachel now out of the picture and לוי
Levi free to do יבום Yibum with דבורה? Devorah? Maybe לוי Levi
should be even free to do יבום Yibum with רחל, Rachel, because
she goes back to being waiting for יבום Yibum or חליצה. Chalitzah.
Okay. So let's take a look. אמר
רבא נתן גט למאמרו, Amar Rava nosan get le-maamaro, he gave a
גט Get to contradict his מאמר, Maamar, to counteract, I should say.
הותרה צרתה, Hutra tzorasa, so the co-wife דבורה Devorah becomes available, אבל
היא, Aval hi, רחל, Rachel, אסורה. Asura. He can't do יבום. Yibum.
He still has to do חליצה Chalitzah obviously because she still hasn't
had יבום Yibum or חליצה Chalitzah done, but he can't do יבום.
Yibum. Why? דמיחלפה בבעלת גט. Demichlifa be-baalas get. Because people will confuse
it for a case of a woman who received a גט Get
on the זיקה. Zika. So here's the הלכה. Okay, you if the
guy did a מאמר Maamar and wants to now separate, he needs
גט Get and חליצה. Chalitzah. The גט Get for the מאמר Maamar
and the חליצה Chalitzah for the זיקה. Zika. If he didn't do
a מאמר Maamar and he doesn't want to do, you know, to
be with this woman, he does חליצה. Chalitzah. That's all that's required,
that's all that's asked. But he has the option of, even if
he didn't do מאמר, Maamar, he has the option of giving her
a גט get as well. And that גט, get it's called a
גט לזיקה, Get le-zika, not a גט למאמר, Get le-maamar, and that
גט get basically says we're, you know, I'm preventing the possibility of
חליצה. Chalitzah. I gave, it's rabbinic, but the גט get is against
the זיקה, Zika, not against the מאמר, Maamar, and it excludes the
possibility of יבום Yibum from that point on. But you still need
חליצה. Chalitzah. He would still have to do חליצה Chalitzah because it
only works דרבנן. De-Rabbanan. So what רבא's Rava saying is even though
this גט get was only to counteract the מאמר, Maamar, we don't
let לוי Levi do יבום Yibum with רחל, Rachel, because רחל Rachel
now is a woman who has received a גט get from one
of the brothers. And who knows whether that was to counteract the
מאמר Maamar or was that a גט get. to the זיקה Zika
and would actually have prevented anybody from doing יבום Yibum with רחל,
Rachel, right? Is that clear? If the גט get was to the
זיקה, Zika, then it would have completely said רחל Rachel should only
get חליצה Chalitzah from the brothers, not יבום. Yibum. So since she
received a גט get even though the גט get was only attached
to the מאמר, Maamar, it looks like a גט to a woman
awaiting חליצה Chalitzah who no longer can receive חליצה, Chalitzah, and therefore,
who no longer can receive יבום, Yibum, and therefore לוי Levi can
only do חליצה Chalitzah with רחל. Rachel.
Why
would you do a גט to זיקה? Zika?
Why would you do that?
Why a גט לזיקה? Get le-zika? זיקה Zika is required, גט to
get out.
Right, so that's what I said, you don't have to, all you
have to do is a חליצה, Chalitzah, but if for whatever reason
the, I mean it's hard to understand why that would happen because
it always seems like a lot more effort to write a גט
than to do a חליצה, Chalitzah, but who knows? So for whatever
reason, let's say, maybe, for whatever reason the rabbi who had the
shoe and who knew how to do חליצה Chalitzah wasn't here, but
your friend the סופר Sofer was here, the woman was demanding and
saying I, you know, whatever it was, some circumstances where you wanted
to make it clear and cut off a certain option. Okay, and
I think I know you don't have the time right now to
do a חליצה Chalitzah but, you know, you got to do this
so we know that you're not doing a יבום. Yibum. So he
wrote the גט and that prevents now and that's seen to rabbinically
counteract the זיקה Zika and to prevent יבום Yibum from taking place.
But you'd still need חליצה.
Chalitzah. He would still need חליצה Chalitzah afterwards. It's only דרבנן. De-Rabbanan.
It's only דרבנן.
De-Rabbanan. Right. Okay. I can't explain the circumstances. But there's some case
where that would be important. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, אמר רבא נתן גט למאמרו, Amar Rava
nosan get le-maamaro, הותרה, Hutra, אפילו היא. Afilu hi. Even רחל Rachel
can now get יבום. Yibum. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? Why? מה דעבד
בה שקליה. Ma d'avad ba shaklei. What he did to her, the
מאמר, Maamar, he took away, and we only, we see it as
completely neutralizing, we don't see it as now changed her status and
looking at her as a בעלת הגט. Baalas ha-get. No, it only
removed the מאמר. Maamar. Now of course the question is how do
you decide whether the גט is addressed just to the מאמר Maamar
or also to the זיקה. Zika. So רש"י Rashi basically says it
just depends on what you say when you do it. Look at
רש"י, Rashi. this little רש"י here where he says, he says,
מה דעבד שקליה, Ma d'avad shaklei, it's like across from the next
משנה Mishna like two lines
down, so מה דעבד שקליה
Ma d'avad shaklei says
רש"י. this גט is only to counteract the מאמר, ma'amar, not to
negate the זיקה. zikah. אבל סתמא קיימא ולא יבנה כולהו אחי. Aval
stama kaima v'lo yivna kulu achei. א סתמא A stama גט
is assumed to be going on the זיקה zikah as well and
to prevent anybody from doing יבום. yibum. Okay. What? In the document?
Yeah, that's a good question. Is it orally or in the document?
I'm not sure. But given that it's so amorphous, you understand רבא's
Rava first position much better, right? It's so unclear whether this is
a גט just for the מאמר, ma'amar, or is this a גט
for the זיקה. zikah. So actually, in some ways, normally all the
דרבננ'ס d'rabbanans and the גזירות gzeiras seem to us a little farfetched.
Here, of all places, it makes a lot of sense to say
it's not so clear whether this is a גט for the מאמר
ma'amar or a גט for the זיקה. zikah. Why
wouldn't we allow it to begin with?
Allow what to begin with?
The גט. The גט has no meaning, the same way קידושין has
no meaning דאורייתא d'oreisa by a יבום yibum case. That's why it's
מאמר. ma'amar. So the only thing the תורה Torah recognizes in this
circumstance is יבום yibum or חליצה. halitzah.
But why wouldn't the דרבנן d'rabanan give the גט the same status
as מאמר? ma'amar?
They do. They do.
So the same way מאמר ma'amar makes her married, then the גט
should give...
yeah, but מאמר ma'amar doesn't fully make her married. That's all the
discussions we've been having. It puts her in a quasi-status.
Okay. All right. Next משנה. Mishnah. שני אחים... Shnei achim... we are
not getting any more caught up. שני אחים נשואים שתי אחיות ומת
אחד מהן. Shnei achim nesuim shtei achayot u'meit echad mehen. Two brothers
married to two sisters, and one dies. ואחר כך מתה אשתו של
שני. V'achar kach meitah ishto shel sheni. Okay, this is an easy
case. Haha. And then the wife of the second one dies. So
here is... this is the whole question about the ערוה, ervah, you
know, the case where... okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon get married
to רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. Okay,
so ראובן Reuven dies. What's רחל's Rachel status?
אחות אשה. Achos isha. ערוה. Ervah. Goodbye. Walk off. But then לאה
Leah died. Oh, maybe she's no longer אחות אשה. achos isha. Maybe
you can go ahead and do יבום. yibum. No, because she was
אחות אשה achos isha at the moment that the יבום yibum became
relevant as her husband died. That's the status that remains. That's what
the משנה Mishnah says. ואחר כך מתה אשתו של שני הרי זו
אסורה עליו עולמית. V'achar kach meitah ishto shel sheni harei zo asurah
alav olamit. רחל Rachel remains eternally forbidden. הואיל ונאסרה עליו שעה אחת.
Ho'il v'neasrah alav sha'ah achat. Because at that critical moment, actually it
says at any moment, but we can even emphasize at the critical
moment, the initial moment, she was forbidden to שמעון. Shimon. So the
גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא. pshita. This is obvious. השתא ומה התם דלא
מדחיא מהאי ביתא לגמרי, Hashta u'ma hatam d'lo midcheya mei-hai beisa l'gamrei,
when she was not completely pushed away from the household... you might
remember that we had the case, it was only yesterday, I think,
where there were three brothers, right? ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי.
Levi. And here you have רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. And what
happens is ראובן Reuven dies.
Then what happens?
Hold on.
I know.
One minute.
Oh, right.
And then לוי Levi marries רחל. Rachel. Okay. And then what happens?
So לוי Levi marries רחל. Rachel. Oh, שמעון Shimon at this stage,
as ראובן Reuven died, okay, רחל Rachel is what's her status? רחל
Rachel is אחות אשה achos isha to שמעון Shimon and totally okay
to לוי, Levi, right? And then לוי Levi goes ahead and marries
her and then does יבום. yibum. לאה Leah dies. לוי Levi dies.
שמעון Shimon remains forbidden. Why does שמעון Shimon remain forbidden? Because at
that early stage
she
was אחות אשה achos isha to him at that early status. So
here the גמרא's Gemara saying, if this case is a problem, then
of course this case is a problem. I mean, you know, here,
even though her relationship to שמעון Shimon was problematic, it wasn't problematic
to לוי, Levi, so she was still somewhat in the פרשה parsha
here. Here, there's only one brother. She's completely אסורה asurah to שמעון.
Shimon. Of course, she's going to remain אסורה. asurah. Okay? So that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. ומה התם דלא מדחיא מהאי ביתא לגמרי, U'ma
hatam d'lo midcheya mei-hai beisa l'gamrei, when she's not completely pushed away
from that family, because לוי Levi is... she's still מותר mutar to
לוי, Levi, אמרת לא, amarta lo, that she's forbidden to שמעון Shimon
because at one stage she was forbidden to
שמעון. Shimon. הכא דקא מדחיא מהאי ביתא לגמרי, Hacha d'ka midcheya mei-hai
beisa l'gamrei, here, that as soon as ראובן Reuven dies she's completely
out of the פרשה, parsha, no brothers... she's not relevant to any
brothers, she walks away, she's out of the פרשה, parsha, so therefore
לא כל שכן? lo kol sheken? Of course this case is going
to be permissible... I mean, forbidden. She's going to be forbidden to
do it and therefore she can just walk away. So the גמרא
says you're right. תנא האי תנא ברישא. Tana hai tana b'reisha. This
case was taught first. This is the more obvious case that רחל
Rachel remains forbidden. והך חזיא ליה v'hach chazyah leih and initially the
גמרא thought that the תנא Tana thought... Initially the גמרא thought that
the תנא thought that this case might be מותר mutar because she
wasn't completely out of the פרשה. parsha. Maybe after לוי Levi marries
her her status changes.
Okay? ושריה. Vesharya. He thought that it was מותר. mutar. והדר חזא
לאיסורא, Vehadar chaza l'isura, and then he decided, no, this case is
also אסור. assur. She was אסור assur once to שמעון, Shimon, she
remains אסור assur to שמעון. Shimon. Okay? ואיידי דחביבא ליה אקדמה, V'aydi
d'chaviva lei akdama, once you decided this was אסור, assur, you didn't
need to teach this משנה. mishna. ואיידי דחביבא ליה אקדמה, V'aydi d'chaviva
lei akdama, because this was a nice big חידוש, chiddush, we put
this case first, which made, we had the same idea before, which
makes this superfluous. ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה, Umishna lo zaza mimkomah, and
therefore we didn't remove this משנה mishna even though now it became
superfluous and obvious. Right?
The גמרא is always saying צריכותא. tzrichuta.
Yeah,
but sometimes it says זו ואין צריך לומר זו. zu v'ein tzarich
lomar zu. So this is a variation of that.